<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-boucadair-netmod-iana-registries-03"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="8407, 8126">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IANA-Maintained YANG Modules">Recommendations for Creating
    IANA-Maintained YANG Modules</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>netmod</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides a set of guidelines for YANG module authors
      related to the design of IANA-maintained modules. These guidelines are
      meant to leverage existing IANA registries and use YANG as another
      format to present the content of these registries when appropriate.</t>

      <t>This document updates RFC 8407 by providing additional guidelines for
      IANA-maintained modules. Also, this document updates RFC 8126 by
      providing additional guidelines for writing the IANA considerations for
      RFCs that specify IANA-maintained modules. This document does not change
      anything written in RFC 8407 and RFC 8126.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>IANA maintains a set of registries that are key for interoperability.
      The content of these registries are usually available using various
      formats (e.g., plain text, XML). However, there were some confusion in
      the past about whether the content of some registries is dependent on a
      specific representation format. For example, Section 5 of <xref
      target="RFC8892"></xref> was published to clarify that MIB and YANG
      modules are merely additional formats in which the "Interface Types
      (ifType)" and "Tunnel Types (tunnelType)" registries are available. The
      MIB <xref target="RFC2863"></xref> and YANG modules <xref
      target="RFC7224"></xref><xref target="RFC8675"></xref> are not separate
      registries, and the same values are always present in all formats of the
      same registry.</t>

      <t>Also, some YANG modules include parameters and values directly in a
      module that is not maintained by IANA while these are populated in an
      IANA registry. Such a design is suboptimal as it creates another source
      of information that may deviate from the IANA registry as new values are
      assigned or some values are deprecated.</t>

      <t>For the sake of consistency, better flexibility to support new
      values, and maintaining IANA registries as the unique authoritative
      source of information, when such an information is maintained in a
      registry, this document encourages the use of IANA-maintained
      modules.</t>

      <t><xref target="update"></xref> updates the guidelines in <xref
      target="RFC8407"></xref>. Also, <xref target="u2"></xref> updates <xref
      target="RFC8407"></xref> and <xref target="RFC8126"></xref> by providing
      guidance for writing the IANA considerations for RFCs that specify
      IANA-maintained modules.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in Section 2 of <xref
      target="RFC8407"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="update" title="Guidelines for IANA-Maintained Modules">
      <t>When designing a YANG module for a functionality governed by a
      protocol for which IANA maintains a registry, it is RECOMMENDED to
      specify an IANA-maintained module that echoes the content of that
      registry. This is superior to including that content in an
      IETF-maintained module.</t>

      <t>When one or multiple sub-registries are available under the same
      registry, it is RECOMMENDED to define an IANA-maintained module for each
      sub-registry. However, module designers MAY consider defining one single
      IANA-maintained module that covers all sub-registries if maintaining
      that single module is manageable (e.g., very few values are present or
      expected to be present for each sub-registry). An example of such a
      module is documented in Section 5.2 of <xref
      target="RFC9132"></xref>.</t>

      <t>An IANA-maintained module may use identities (e.g., <xref
      target="RFC8675"></xref>) or enumerations (e.g., <xref
      target="RFC9108"></xref>). The decision about which type to use is left
      to the module designers and should be made based upon specifics related
      to the intended use of the IANA-maintained module. For example,
      identities are useful if the registry entries are organized
      hierarchically, possibly including multiple inheritances. It is
      RECOMMENDED that the reasoning for the design choice is documented in
      the companion specification that registers an IANA-maintained module.
      For example, <xref target="RFC9244"></xref> defines an IANA-maintained
      module that uses enumerations for the following reason:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[  "The DOTS telemetry module (Section 10.1) uses "enumerations" rather
   than "identities" to define units, samples, and intervals because
   otherwise the namespace identifier "ietf-dots-telemetry" must be
   included when a telemetry attribute is included (e.g., in a
   mitigation efficacy update).  The use of "identities" is thus
   suboptimal from a message compactness standpoint; one of the key
   requirements for DOTS messages."]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Designers of IANA-maintained modules MAY supply the full initial
      version of the module in a specification document that registers the
      module or only a script to be used (including by IANA) for generating
      the module (e.g., an XSLT stylesheet as in Appendix A of <xref
      target="RFC9108"></xref>). When a script is used, the Internet-Draft
      that defines an IANA-maintained module SHOULD include an appendix with
      the initial full version of the module. Including such an appendix in
      pre-RFC versions is meant to assess the correctness of the outcome of
      the supplied script. The authors MUST include a note to the RFC Editor
      requesting that the appendix be removed before publication as RFC.
      Initial versions of IANA-maintained modules that are published in RFCs
      may be misused despite the appropriate language to refer to the IANA
      registry to retrieve the up-to-date module. This is problematic for
      interoperability, e.g., when values are deprecated or are associated
      with a new meaning. <list style="empty">
          <t>Note: <xref target="Style"></xref> provides XSLT 1.0 stylesheets
          and other tools for translating IANA registries to YANG modules. The
          tools can be used to generate up-to-date revisions of an
          IANA-maintained module based upon the XML representation of an IANA
          registry.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="u2"
             title="Guidance for Writing the IANA Considerations for RFCs Defining IANA-Maintained Modules">
      <t>In addition to the IANA considerations in Section 3.8 of <xref
      target="RFC8407"></xref>, the IANA Considerations Section of an RFC that
      includes an IANA-maintained module MUST provide the required
      instructions for IANA to automatically perform the maintenance of that
      IANA module. These instructions describe how to proceed with updates to
      the IANA-maintained module that are triggered by a change to the
      authoritative registry. Concretely, the IANA Considerations Section
      SHALL at least provide the following information: </t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>An IANA request to add a note to the page displaying the
          information about the IANA-maintained module that new values must
          not be directly added to the module, but to an authoritative IANA
          registry.</t>

          <t>An IANA request to add a note to the authoritative IANA registry
          to indicate that any change to the registry must be reflected into
          the corresponding IANA-maintained module. </t>

          <t>Details about the required actions (e.g., add a new "identity" or
          "enum" statement) to update the IANA-maintained module to reflect
          changes to an authoritative IANA registry. Typically, these details
          have to include the procedure to create a new "identity" statement
          name and sub-statements ("base", "status", "description", and
          "reference") or a new "enum" statement and sub-statements ("value",
          "status", "description", and "reference"). </t>

          <t>A note that unassigned or reserved values must not be present in
          the IANA-maintained module.</t>

          <t>An indication whether experimental values are included in the
          IANA-maintained module. Absent such an indication, experimental
          values MUST NOT be listed in the IANA-maintained module. </t>

          <t>An instruction about how to generate the "revision" statement.
          </t>
        </list></t>

      <t>A template for the IANA Considerations is provided in <xref
      target="tem1"></xref> for IANA-maintained modules with identities and
      <xref target="tem2"></xref> for IANA-maintained modules with
      enumerations. Authors may modify the template to reflect specifics of
      their modules (e.g., Multiple registries can be listed for a single
      IANA-maintained module, no explicit description (or name) field is
      listed under the authoritative IANA registry).</t>

      <t>The following templates are to be considered in addition to the
      required information that is provided in Section 3.8 of <xref
      target="RFC8407"></xref>.</t>

      <section anchor="tem1"
               title="Template for IANA-Maintained Modules with Identities">
        <t>This document defines the initial version of the IANA-maintained
        "iana-foo" YANG module. The most recent version of the YANG module is
        available from the "YANG Parameters" registry <xref
        target="IANA-YANG-PARAMETERS"></xref>.</t>

        <t>IANA is requested to add this note to the registry:<list
            style="empty">
            <t>New values must not be directly added to the "iana-foo" YANG
            module. They must instead be added to the "foo" registry.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When a value is added to the "foo" registry, a new "identity"
        statement must be added to the "iana-foo" YANG module. The name of the
        "identity" is the lower-case of the name provided in the registry. The
        "identity" statement should have the following sub-statements
        defined:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="&quot;base&quot;:">Contains
            'name-base-identity-defined-in-foo'.</t>

            <t hangText="&quot;status&quot;:">Include only if a registration
            has been deprecated or obsoleted. IANA "deprecated" maps to YANG
            status "deprecated", and IANA "obsolete" maps to YANG status
            "obsolete".</t>

            <t hangText="&quot;description&quot;:">Replicates the description
            from the registry.</t>

            <t hangText="&quot;reference&quot;:">Replicates the reference(s)
            from the registry with the title of the document(s) added.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Unassigned or reserved values are not present in the module.</t>

        <t>When the "iana-foo" YANG module is updated, a new "revision"
        statement with a unique revision date must be added in front of the
        existing revision statements.</t>

        <t>IANA is requested to add this note to
        [reference-to-the-iana-foo-registry]:</t>

        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>When this registry is modified, the YANG module "iana-foo" must
            be updated as defined in RFCXXXX.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tem2"
               title="Template for IANA-Maintained Modules with Enumerations">
        <t>This document defines the initial version of the IANA-maintained
        "iana-foo" YANG module. The most recent version of the YANG module is
        available from the "YANG Parameters" registry <xref
        target="IANA-YANG-PARAMETERS"></xref>.</t>

        <t>IANA is requested to add this note to the registry:<list
            style="empty">
            <t>New values must not be directly added to the "iana-foo" YANG
            module. They must instead be added to the "foo" registry.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When a value is added to the "foo" registry, a new "enum" statement
        must be added to the "iana-foo" YANG module. The "enum" statement, and
        sub-statements thereof, should be defined:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="&quot;enum&quot;:">Replicates a name from the
            registry.</t>

            <t hangText="&quot;value&quot;:">Contains the decimal value of the
            IANA-assigned value.</t>

            <t hangText="&quot;status&quot;:">Is included only if a
            registration has been deprecated or obsoleted. IANA "deprecated"
            maps to YANG status "deprecated", and IANA "obsolete" maps to YANG
            status "obsolete".</t>

            <t hangText="&quot;description&quot;:">Replicates the description
            from the registry.</t>

            <t hangText="&quot;reference&quot;:">Replicates the reference(s)
            from the registry with the title of the document(s) added.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Unassigned or reserved values are not present in the module.</t>

        <t>When the "iana-foo" YANG module is updated, a new "revision"
        statement with a unique revision date must be added in front of the
        existing revision statements.</t>

        <t>IANA is requested to add this note to
        [reference-to-the-iana-foo-registry]:</t>

        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>When this registry is modified, the YANG module "iana-foo" must
            be updated as defined in RFCXXXX.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require any IANA action. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce new concerns other than those
      already discussed in Section 15 of <xref target="RFC8407"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is triggered by a discussion the author had with Dhruv
      Dhody and Jensen Zhang.</t>

      <t>Thanks to J&uuml;rgen Sch&ouml;nw&auml;lder, Ladislav Lhotka, and Qin
      Wu for the discussion and valuable comments. Special thanks to Ladislav
      Lhotka for sharing more context that led to the design documented in
      <xref target="RFC9108"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Andy Bierman for the comments. Lou Berger suggested to
      include more details about IANA considerations. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8407'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8126'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9132'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8675'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8892'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9108'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9244'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2863'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7224'?>

      <reference anchor="Style" target="https://github.com/llhotka/iana-yang">
        <front>
          <title>IANA YANG</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA YANG</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="" year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IANA-YANG-PARAMETERS"
                 target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/yang-parameters">
        <front>
          <title>YANG Parameters</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="" year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
